[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
hi this is priyanka ragman for software
engineering radio the guest andy powell
and me work for the same organization
musk
hi everyone this is priyanka raghvan for
software engineering radio and today we
have an exciting topic to explore
lessons learned from a major cyber
attack and for that please welcome my
guest andy powell
andy is the chief information security
officer of ap moller musk the world's
largest shipping conglomerate
he is accountable for all aspects of
information security and cyber security
and prior to joining musk andy was with
capgemini as the head of cyber security
and before that he used to be
engineering officer and then you know
went on to serve as the cso for the uk
royal air force he's also the head of
cyber defense operations for the uk
ministry of defense welcome to the show
andy we're just really glad to have you
priyanka many many thanks yeah i was a
bit worried with introductions like that
makes me feel very
okay so of course my first question to
you before we actually go on to the
attack which hit mers because could you
introduce the audience to musk and tell
us a little bit about uh what they do
and also about the technology that is
used so yeah ap monomers kids um many
people would have seen the immersive
logo on the side of uh iso containers
going around
we moved 20 percent of the world trade
we are the biggest container company in
the world uh approximately 750 vessels
uh which we operate we also uh operate
within 70 plus ports internals around
the globe
some of which we own
some of which we're part partners in
we also have quite a significant
warehouse capability as well for onward
transmission of cargo but really the
most important thing is that we also
move 33 of the world's bananas
one of three of the bananas that you eat
was to move by musk so
that's always a quite an interesting
fact i always use when uh when i work
with that i think the main thing is that
nurse operates in 120 plus countries
globally
and clearly given our critical role in
world trade you know we are a
significant capability and also a
significant target
as i'm sure we'll cover very very
shortly in terms of technology i guess
you have like a lot of these iot devices
on your ships and vessels and also the
terminals so
yeah so today um so if we compare today
to where we were even three years ago
attack itself we'll come on to that as
i'm sure within a few questions yeah
yes we have a significant if you can
imagine we have a very significant it
capability around running our business
so we use quite significant range of
technologies from sap to microservice
api type technologies to rit
and runs a quite significant
range of capabilities but also on the ot
or operational technology side we
clearly have a significant range of ot
capability and we're instrumenting a lot
of that at the moment with iot networks
those iot networks really are utilizing
cloud technology as well
and we have to protect and provide
protection across those networks and if
you can imagine those ot networks or our
vessels
they're on any of our cranes and we have
cranes in our terminals each of those
has an ot device on board to control the
actual crane itself uh right down to the
fact that a number of our ports are
fully automated in a couple of locations
like
rotterdam we have a fully automated
terminal and all of those of course have
uh ot devices so a significant
technology
right and a huge attack surface as you
say so yeah raise a very very good point
of course the attack surface itself has
grown exponentially in the last three
years
three years ago for two reasons one is
our digital footprint we're now
operating a vast range of digital
services
because the volunteers we'll discuss of
those is is the client given identity
credentials to access services through
the digital platforms
that represents a massive increase in
our attack surface the side of course is
the same challenge with the massive
expansion of iot to monitor and
instruments the ot network that in
itself has increased our attack service
really really soon
okay so obviously now we have to get to
the chunk of the what we want to talk
about which is the attack and i remember
reading this article on wired when the
attack happened and it said the untold
story of notepathy the most devastating
cyber attack in history that sounds
scary so could you tell us
what happened on that day yeah i think
the most important thing is that never
believe what you read in the press
thing
and clearly i've as i came into musk six
months after the attack i was able to
sort of fully understand through the
analysis and forensics that carried out
what had happened but let's let's go
back to and also just destroy some of
the misconceptions that came out of the
the wide article which which actually
was incorrect in a number of ways i
think the most thing was that musk was
very transparent throughout the attack
we we unlike many companies who were hit
at the time and even those who've been
hit since we were very open both with
our clients
customers but also with our partners you
know our technology partners in
particular we involved them we were very
open with them and that was an important
lesson we'll come on to
but let's go back to the day in question
that that june day in 2017 when
basically what had happened is the
attack itself was sold six months before
it actually happened and for many who
read the press it was very clear that
the the root of entry was was well
planned so
if those who don't know what it was it's
what it says on the tin it wasn't petya
otherwise it was not a ransomware attack
it was a cyber weapon
designed by nation state to cause
disruption significant disruption its
target was ukraine
and their aim was to disrupt ukrainian
tax system and government system and
also during a holiday period that was
due to occur in june in ukraine and that
weapon was launched that very single
reason the weapon itself looks like a
ransomware reality it was it was not
and and it was the way they used it was
uh a piece of software
called medox which was the ukrainian tax
software and this is a lesson for all of
us by the way for all of us who use tax
software to send our tax returns it was
worth knowing this is third-party
software and for many of your listeners
this is a sanitary lesson that all
software can be targeted and it doesn't
mean you have to go directly into the
software that company's using you can
use third-party software and get your
malware into that and then of course the
company who wants to use that software
uploads it into their network through a
third party and this is what happened
the medoc software which which was we
were using to submit our tax returns to
the ukrainian government
like many other uh western national
companies that software was basically
got out six months before by the state
in question
who basically got the malware through an
employee of the meetings
an individual basically places placed
the malware into into a software upgrade
and that software upgrade went in place
in june 2017 it uploaded the nonpeggy
market and that then infected
many many multinational companies
including burst who were operating in
ukraine and within about seven minutes
to an hour the damage was done
globally so your audience understand how
this malware operates
nation-state weapons like this
don't hang around once they're activated
they're quite quite they move very very
quickly
and they move they move quickly
horizontally they move across networks
and in this case there were four
elements to the malware weapon
which operated and this is widely
publicized
a couple of those elements were things
that maybe could have been stopped if
you had the latest software upgrades the
latest patches and windows and the
windows os
but most companies don't most companies
are operating a version of windows
that's maybe one behind one
most companies were not operating
windows 10
which windows 10 would have prevented
about 80 percent of this but
unfortunately the 20 percent will got
through couldn't have been stopped
because it was aimed at some underlying
infrastructure within microsoft software
and it was that was exploited by the
weapon and that that allowed the weapon
to move so rapidly across people's
networks
so really by the background it was it
was not a ransomware it looked like
ransomware it asked for a bitcoin ransom
paid to release the data but in reality
very little bitcoin was ever retrieved
or paid what the weapon did was bring
people's networks down what it did very
very simply was obfuscate the what were
known as the microsoft tables so the
tables that many people are aware of
that operate your system through active
directory dns servers particularly dns
service
that was basically what they got at uh
and basically what prevented
people's networks from operating
it took us
two to three days to get our active
directory capability running again if
you're aware of the story
probably many have heard of this
all our online backup was also built out
by the malware so the weapon itself to
take out our existing network he was
able to attack our online backups backup
as well oh my god okay
we basically were like many companies
globally reliance on online backup
that was taken down and the weapon
targeted our active directory notes
significantly which meant that
at the time within a day or two we
thought that's it we have no active
directory nodes they've all been taken
out we have no backups because they've
been taken down
we can't restart the network because
without
image on an active directory it was
going to be impossible to restart the
network and so basically we were pretty
close to
saying that's it
we can't go much further
fortunately for us in lagos in nigeria
there had been a power outage just as
the attack occurred
which had meant that the active
directory node in lagos was not online
at the time
so had a complete copy of an active
directory note in lagos and and that was
put on a first-class seating aircraft
and from the uk probably the most
well-traveled and well-looked after
server that's
and it allowed us to replicate the
active directory from it so that we
could basically replicate that to all
the ad nodes that we built
but really let's if i go back one the
damage that had been done was
significant we're talking about 40 000.
thousand servers taken down
a thousand plus applications were
taken down
you know we had no telephone because all
our telephones are based through the
network right
so just to reiterate it's something like
more than some 40 000 endpoints your
telephones were down um
yeah thousand plus applications were
down
wow longer
recover from all of this
so so the basic recovery period was in
three phases really the first three to
four days was building if you like the
central core again we had to rebuild the
central core of the network through the
ad nodes and then we had to then if you
like replicate that by buying
effectively all the laptops we could
find
start the network so we bought most of
the laptops in the uk in india and
elsewhere and we then had to replicate
what we had built from main head out
into the various regions that took us
between nine days to two weeks so it was
that sort of length of time to get our
core uh network and processes back up
and running again
and
we wouldn't be able to do that to be
honest without the help of our partners
at the time so we had ibm as our main
network partner who was superb leading
in to help us we had microsoft who did a
great helping us as well so
we wouldn't have been able to do it at
that time at that scale without the
golden one partners plus also the
patience of our customers just your
listeners all our iso containers so one
of our tripoli vessels moves 19 024 iso
containers per ship it ships to
customers all of that
we don't have the computer
we don't know what's inside each
container
we have no we have no record
so in many cases these containers had to
be opened so we can know what was inside
them who the consignment was for
and that level of manual intervention
into processes took most of
because we had to work out where our key
loads were particularly our refrigerator
contains and we had to
ensure they were prioritized for our
clients many of our clients were very
keen to get their
get their cargo
again i listen to your clients you know
software rules the world but when the
software doesn't work
um
to
manual processes and that's very very
painful
right
obviously we'll have to like now you
know talk about about this recovery
process and what you learned from that
so for example now this kind of thing
that you're talking about this notepad
yeah you know between like the
state-sponsored
attack
i mean how do companies actually go
ahead and you know sort of
model for that or you know try to take
those threats into consideration
i think you've asked a really great
question because there are three
probably three groups of threats that
most modern good companies like nurse
face today the most obvious and
prevalent threat about 80 percent of our
threat comes from organized crime
so organized criminality basically got
their hands on some quite advanced cyber
weapons
and some quite advanced malware
and their intent is to basically steal
money i mean organized crime is about
making money from trying
their main aims to either steal or
provide ransomware to try and get you
know extort money from from targets and
their victims so most of those weapons
are the ones that we clearly plan to try
and prevent because clearly we're not
about to pay out money to these folks we
don't so what we do is we built our
protection around that sort of 80 threat
if that makes sense as i mentioned there
are two other threats that we face today
the other threat i've just talked about
was nation state i should say weapons
are
really in two types they're the
disruptive type weapons which you know
not petty or was that they're target
used by states against their enemies to
disrupt their economies or disrupt them
we immersed ourselves probably wouldn't
be targeted by those as we weren't
if we were a collateral victim of
somebody else's weapon if that makes
sense and that can happen any time we
have to be on the have to be wary of
that so i'll explain how we do that in a
second and the third threat is for what
we call hacktivists there's extinction
rebellion and others
who basically use denial of service type
attacks to try and bring down
companies like merck and others who they
believe you know causing global problems
and so we have to be ready for those
level of attacks now those three groups
of threats need different treatments
so like many companies what we do is we
design
to protect ourselves against the most
prevalent threats and we also build a
combination of protection or
proactive protection
and reactive modules so to go back to my
point we have offline backup now backup
processes where we can use excel and
other type capabilities to replicate
systems that might be disrupted so if
the weapon gets through and clearly some
of these nation state weapons could be
very very difficult to stop
and at the time very few people could
have stopped not pettying in fact only
governments probably would have been
able to stop not petty type malware and
for companies like us to try and stop it
would be prohibitively expensive and
difficult so we have to design measures
to recover much more quickly so when
it's nine days to recover from a
multiplicity type attack in the future
no we could do it much much more quickly
but because we've designed recovery
management measures to do that what we
have built proactive measures to stop
most of the organized crime attacks for
good reason those protective measures
try and stop them at the front door
right and so that's how we've reacted
we've looked at the range of threats and
then we built processes around handling
that risk
so there's also this concept of what you
call a red teaming um that security
teams talk about like you know so we are
predominantly a software engineering
audience but could you tell the audience
a little bit about what red tape teaming
is and you know how can that prepare for
these kind of attacks and in fact this
is a good one for your audience actually
because
they have a role to play in the red
teaming approach so like most companies
built a cyber threat capability within
the company the ability to evaluate
threats
and if you like test ourselves
and self-testing is really quite
important for many companies
in the old days they used to call it
penetration testing which is
basically where you had teams trying to
get in in our eyes the run penetration
testing teams were asked to cap gemini
and the idea of the team was that their
aim is to get into a company's
network
often
nine times out of ten we didn't need to
hack into the network we just send
somebody through the front door
reception and they would often find a
password written on someone's desk and
to be honest you know why would you
spend a lot of money and time trying to
hack in if if actually you could just go
and steal somebody's login
credentials and so
you know that's my issue the second is
you know the exploitation of
vulnerabilities in network and that's
that's coming on to the point about red
teaming
there are vulnerabilities in your
network that you often don't
believe you could have and i'm afraid a
lot of pauses are what we call back
doors or you know software programming
errors and what we tend to uncover is
vulnerabilities are often self-created
it's just poor software design you know
many of your audience will be aware of
the sorts of sequel type injection
attacks the sql injection is very simply
somebody poorly designing uh the field
in a form so it
can be you know
it and and can it bring it can bring
down a database very very easy if you
don't put the right limits on on that
particular form that's just poor design
you know one of the key things is these
red teams that we hire in often my sole
job is to go and look for those
vulnerabilities and try and exploit them
okay then use hacking algorithms you
know off supercomputers to be honest
they're going to go and look for
backdoors that have been left by
software engineers and others they're
going to go and look for poor software
design and we're going to explore them
we tend to do is use the red teams to
try and think laterally as well they'll
go and look in places that we might not
have thought of
right for example
macros which i hate by the way which
i use a lot
to make their jobs easier but what does
a macro represent it's a piece of
software that's been designed to
automate its role or task
people use them all over the place to
sort of link
application
link processes together they don't
document they don't tell us what they've
done they don't tell us where they are
and so we tend to use our red teams to
go in and look for those pieces of quote
software that we've been trying to put
in to make life easier they have not
been documented so
again a bit of a call to the audience
you know documents
but the red teams are there to exploit
it they're there too to
find ways
so we hire them because they think like
attackers
reality is you've got to find what we
call white hat hackers they're good
people whose sole job is to come and
find holes and gaps
in this show we've also talked about
things like secure by design and you
know starting security a little early in
the development life cycle so i'm sure
you guys are doing it at mask but is
there um any thoughts you have on does
it make sense to do this early is there
a way to measure success
yes there is and um there are a number
of ways of doing it so
the one thing i've learned in life is
there's no one single solution to a
problem it generally means multiple
solutions applied and it's the same here
it's if we if we just simply look at
software design in itself the software
development life cycle the old sdlc
process which i say old we're now in the
development type cycles that people are
using but we still get a lot of
conventional sdlc we've now clearly got
much more depth processes developing
those processes
are
exploitable okay
if executed poorly
and so there's a number of things we
provide and it's probably four layers
that we look at today which i'm sure
audience will many of them will be
experienced with we've created a sku by
design hub where we provide solutions to
those four issues the first is where do
i go to get approved code code that i
can reuse that i know is security
checked cleared already so i don't have
to do it myself
so you know we create secure code that
they can download and reuse how much
we've been
reused that we know is secure
that that's good and so secure apis for
instance you know
go to a secure api library and you know
you've got an api that's already been
checked and cleared what that does is it
doesn't replicate
the network so that's the first solution
the second is what we call patterns with
software engineer the first thing you're
looking for is somebody give me a
pattern to operate
a good pattern
and we will build secure patterns for
them as well so they'll provide those
secure patterns in the spd hub the idea
is they can go and get those secure
patterns and use them to build the code
and those are approved security patterns
as well that they can reuse and then
thirdly is testing tools that they can
self-test okay what i hate absolutely
loads
is the development process stopping and
calling in a security person
testing for them
why would we do that why don't we get
the developers to test their own code as
they do anyway
alongside the normal tools they use for
testing so that the process includes
security testing software guys can can
operate
and that's the issue
the problem is as many of your audience
will know
one tool can't fix all the software
we've got there's different forms of
software that you've got to provide
testing for like sap type software
testing api and microservices testing
sort of more conventional code testing
all of them need different tools and
again we can provide those tools in the
secure by design hub they can be
downloaded and used by the developers
there's a really good piece and then the
fourth bit is what i call penetration
testing
again why don't you have self contracts
that are already in place for the
developer just to get in a third party
to do a bit of testing of their code as
they go with penetration testing so that
those back doors i talked about are
looked at how do they develop the
modules
and then build the whole thing and then
penetration test it afterwards i'd
rather the penetration testing as we go
and then that way
when you launch to production
so they're the four key things that
we're desperately trying to get in place
today
you know if we can get all that up and
running like many companies it eases the
whole process
and also security people being the bad
people we are bad people you know the
developers see us as they as the people
are going to come along
roadblock
i don't need to be the bad person
i want to be the good person who's
helping
ensure there's no roadblocks
yeah that's well said yeah because um
most developers think of you know
security as well as qa which i think
right now is you know it's changing in
our agile way of working people who are
you know adding impediments to the job
so you know so that's a good thing to
say so we did a show on devsecops like
back in 2017 and that was like what
you're talking about like you know
trying to incorporate security into the
development life cycle can you talk us
through a little bit about that you know
your experience at mosque how's it been
or you know when previously your
organizations how's that worked
yeah it's but as i mentioned already
frankie the problem with companies like
maersk and others is that we have a
legacy landscape to sustain many of your
listeners will know sitting in most
organizations you'll have a range of
different types of code additional
mainframe based applications some may
completely still run them
existing sort of multi-standard sort of
monolithic built applications that
you've just added to over the years it's
a non-modular way then you've got your
modern dev type evolution feature-based
type development which again is great
and then you've got your sap
solutions which come pretty low and then
you add modules to et cetera so you know
just imagine that landscape and then
just the iot issue that you and i talked
about earlier yes
you've got little bits of code operating
in the ot system and
monitoring some of the iot networks and
again
that is exploitable psychology so that
is a landscape that a company like
maersk and many others sort of face
today many of your audience will be
familiar with that so we have to develop
solutions for each of those different
approach
we so do a lot of traditional code
testing in our monolithic applications
we still do a lot of
a lot of a simple standard approach you
would see many in many places because
you have to
you know
and your experience as well i'm sure in
your area is that all the applications
need to be
as i said need to be fed and watered and
then of course you've got your devs
professors we've talked about what we
need in place for that but then you've
got your challenges of sap which of
course is quite a complicated core and
then trying to understand how you test
into the core of that is a challenge and
then finally you've got your iot space
which is
and i'll give you an example
you know some of the controllers that we
uncovered are windows xp
wow okay most of your audience we sat
there really
don't even start me on the 3.1 stuff
you know we have uncovered sort of
software os standards that are variable
in the ot space so if you can imagine
software base
to start your testing from because deal
with the legacy landscape means you've
got to be you've got to be smart you've
got to do it in different ways different
areas
and to your audience who are sort of
growing up in the dev world most
companies are not startups with digital
development as their main area a lot of
companies like ours
have that legacy landscape it's
important that people are trained and
prepared to operate in those different
areas
so they're the sorts of lessons and
challenges we're facing today it's
exciting
i'd love to be a young developer today
coming into that sort of environment you
know every day would be a different
challenge i think
we had a uh episode a few weeks back on
mobile security testing and that was
also you know like the kind of different
os's that are coming out for you know
cell phones is also
you know you need to support all of that
so i can just imagine how
how it must be at your company
obviously now we are in this pandemic in
this work from home situation and things
like that and then um i was reading this
article about google where you know
right now what they do is like they've
you know just done away with vpns for
all their employees so just to sort of
test their you know security it's a zero
trust network so obviously i need to ask
you as i see so what's your views on
zero trust network would you go the
google way at some point
it's interesting
interestingly developed i've joined it
in a number of forums i think it depends
a lot on the risk appetite in your
company different companies have people
risk appetites different companies have
different risk landscapes
are you going to operate that sort of
open network probably not
for a number of reasons if you're a
government organization you'll probably
have a similar sort of level of risk
have a better risk appetite than others
i think appetite is what determines how
you want to operate
second point is
what's the hostile threat to you
who is the likely group
homeworking has been a really good
example you know most companies like
ourselves have seen a rapid increase in
phishing type attacks the bad folks know
we're working from home therefore
people working from home
don't take the same care that you would
in the office it's a pretty standard
thing you you know how many of you have
used your mobile phone personal
applications on your mobile phone to
maybe send a document because you can't
get your network working at home
certainly say hello i'll just send it
off my iphone or send it off my personal
computer
before you know what you've just done is
you just
moved official documents across
a largely unprotected personal network
so i'm afraid
xero trust
requires lots of education training and
awareness this requires a degree of
baked in security and an assurance that
painted security is there in the
products you're using very many products
that we use are not
as safe as people think they are a good
example is zoom and until
halfway through the pandemic people
didn't realize just how
poor
zoo was you know as a tool it was using
processes that restoring private
cloud environment
you know these are the sorts of things
you uncover you can do zero trust in it
if you come to a world
where
you know the elements that you're using
are secure
zero trust and trust and trust-based
networks are about accepting the fact
that somebody offers you something that
you know is good
and i don't trust a developer in another
company no offense
until i've tested it and yes there's big
overhead because we're not trusting each
other because we don't really
share and
use open processes
and yes do we move
i mean it's a great debate a number of
years ago about linux and those and the
many of your audience would have been in
and would have gone hey that's the way
ahead we all shared the code we did the
code together it made it much more
secure
than the stuff that's developed behind
closed doors we made it secure because
we worked on it to make it secure
absolutely but then what happened is
linux then got packaged to be sold and
what then happens people create their
bespoke versions of linux none of which
was then open and visible to others and
the minute you don't make things open
is the minute you've lost trust
so
long-winded answer to an excellent
question but we don't live in a world
that is perfect
because we have to put in place some
checks and balances
and home working has shown that those
checks and balances are still needed you
know so we like many companies operate a
vpn based network we downloaded
significant endpoint security for our
home workers we've helped them with
their network security in their own
homes because we know their wi-fi
security has got to be has got to be
improved we've done all of that because
i'm afraid
yeah because you know you know the
consequences of something going wrong so
yeah that's also there right
so what must you create overhead is
right of course of course
can't make it difficult for users
because i'm sure most of your audience
know the minute you make it difficult
for users what do they do they don't use
it right
the next thing you know they're using
their own home computer and they're
talking work and they're passing
documents
into using suit because that the bad
company is ban zoom
we don't want that we've got to find
ways of embracing the tools they need to
want to use
secure so that they can use them
properly so get that
spread
you know it's it's amazing how much
we're in sync because i the question i
was going to ask you next was in terms
of designing there's always a play
between security and usability right if
you really make something too secure
essentially this at a point where you
can't even enter the application then
yeah your application is gone right
whatever you're designing or the success
of it is how usable it is so the
question is a little bit long-winded in
the sense that uh like one of the
aspects of you know looking at usability
and you know looking at statistics of
how user behavior is and then designing
your system is that something that's
also being done with of course security
in mind
this is a great question because i think
this is important for your listeners as
well because
you know software engineers have got to
think
how do i want this to be used and when
they're designing what they're designing
their code their features their their
product they've got to think how do i
want this to be used put yourself in the
user's shoes coming in how do they want
to access data how do you do today can
you go on amazon to buy something you
want them to present you with a bunch of
recently purchased products because you
might want to rebuy it i think you want
to easily provide you with a list of
similar products you might be interested
in because you might be interested in so
there's a lot of what we call analytics
behavior
and you've seen it in modern platforms
today they jump ahead of you they use
data as a means to provide what you want
and what that's meant is that user
expectations
your audience know are very high
they don't want to have to hunt for
stuff and look for sleep
easily
so when we design security we have to
think exactly the same way
multi-factor authentication is a good
example if you go to your bank today
most banks use multi-factor as they
should you'll do a transaction you'll
get a they'll send you an independent
message on your phone with a code that
code has to be entered back into your
computer having you logged into the
system so you've got multi-factor
if they make that process too difficult
you can't get access to the services and
people will say i don't want to use that
company they made it too difficult for
me to get in i'll go and use somebody
who's much easier and the problems with
the company that doesn't use
multi-factors that they're probably
exposed to greater threat and your stuff
is at greater risk so you've got to make
the multi-factor journey in that case
much simpler and easy to use okay and i
get really frustrated because i live in
a place with bad mobile coverage so if
they send me on my mobile i may not get
the code because my mobile's not picking
up code and i can't get into the service
i've got to allow for that in your
design so i've they've designed it so
automatic calls my next my home phone
landline which immediately means i know
there's a backup so
you've got to design these journeys
these multi-factor journeys or the
security journeys so that you don't
scare people away and when you scare
people away right they go and use
services which are poor
that are not well protected and that's
what the bad guys are hoping you'll do
that they're all i mean good example is
paypal you know it's paypal but i'm
afraid you know paypal is still catching
up on its security journey is it as
protected as your bank probably not and
people attempt to use these third-party
payment apps these third-party payment
systems because they're much easier
seemingly to use but in reality
they're maybe not well protected but
we've got to think about making the user
journey through the security piece much
easier many of your audience will be
saying why do we use passwords because i
have to remember the password i have to
write it down or um why don't we just
use biometrics you know so i can use my
iris my computer camera
make that why can't you make that easier
for me and the answer is good
but but unfortunately you know the
technology isn't quite there yet uh we
would like to do it that way we'd like
to use multi-factor with biometrics we'd
like to find ways and means and making
that journey much easier because we know
that passwords
are easily exploitable you know 90
passwords are insecure they're very
important
most bad guys know how to break password
chains very very easily so
we've got to find a better way of doing
that for example but we have to find a
way of doing that it's easy for the user
so they don't find a biometric device to
put their thumb prints on or it doesn't
get a bit of grease on it and it doesn't
work and they can't get into the
application so
they've got to find ways and means of
solving those engineering problems
so are you or do you actually employ
people uh who go and talk to your
clients to see how to make a better sort
of journey in terms of security is that
what you do with the companies the
vendors decide yes because
i'm selling cyber solutions to companies
right so i wanted to make i wanted some
selling points some unique selling
products that didn't make nice
and a good example for many of your
audiences i go back to my digital
frontier
what is the new frontier of people's
networks companies networks it's not
it's not firewalls and network security
anymore it's identity and access
management right exactly yes
so we need to go and talk to the vendors
who are providing iodine solutions and
say how do we make them customer
friendly so how does a customer coming
into my website wanting to access a
service and book a container and get
data on that container how do i make
that journey
easy how do i that i
do the identity and access for them in a
seamless way how do i secure the data
using pki and other standards that
they're sending to me and back how do i
ensure that their data in my network is
secured and easy to access um how do i
walk through that customer journey and
we do yes use companies to help us do
that there are lots of third-party
companies out there who will walk you
through the journey of a customer and
say
our customer will react
and it's a bit like red teaming but from
a client perspective right right right
right
okay using those sorts of methodologies
okay i was also curious in terms of
nowadays that you talked about analytics
you have a lot of this data that i'm
sure you're collecting uh but you use
the that for also uh in terms of you
know studying threats so is that uh this
is specific kind of do you look at that
kind of uh
we use third parties to help us there
okay absolutely
companies out there
who provide data
which
is to help us analyze
the threat environment and the user
environment
clearly the data we use is is fully
cleared through privacy laws and privacy
laws where we use data
but the data we often get from
third-party companies is is analyzed
through third-party tools that help us
understand
uh patterns of behavior threat patterns
et cetera patterns is key to see aware
in in worldly living you know you've got
to look at patterns of behavior patterns
of use you've got to look for changes in
those patterns because that often is an
indicator of something that might not
quite good
so for instance if a customer's behavior
in logging into the network changes
because that indicates if they normally
log in
in the morning in the afternoon to book
containers and check their container
moves and then suddenly you're seeing a
range of logins through the day
significantly increase that that gives
you a bit of an indicator that maybe
either something's happened on the
client side or somebody is using client
access to get into your network and
those are the sorts of signs you've got
to look for you know
uh unusual routines because that then
helps us
uh rapidly uh proactively then go and
look for brilliant friends
so i guess what you're talking about is
like you're looking for these patterns
but so are you like having these fancy
like what they show in these hollywood
movies like a really cool operating
center where you know you have these
many screens where you're looking at hey
that container looks odd behavior is
that what i mean what's that tell us a
window into that i mean interesting i
think companies like ourselves they're
no different to many other couples
we have a triple c as it's called which
is our uh
we also have global cyber defense center
and they are multi-screened when our
people are
are in them they look very
and we're able to access them so all the
capability has just been accessed
remotely at the moment but but in the
same way it's very effective but yes in
those screens so the triple c for
instance is monitoring application
behaviors all the time they're looking
at how applications have been accessed
they're looking at how those
applications are operating and we're
able to collect a lot of data on
application use a lot of data on network
on how things are operating and that
allows us to to create
you know pictures
you're right yeah it's a bit
hollywood-like i wish i wish i had the
sort of money to create those hollywood
supersets but in reality we've got a
pretty good capability that allows us to
have good eyes on
lots of those statistics lots of those
use patterns and my analysts my tier 3
and tier 2 analysts are very smart folks
they can immediately spot something
unusual
in the collection of those logs so we do
that like most security company uh
companies we collect security logs uh
and we analyze those logs using software
allows spot patterns in in how the
people are accessing various
applications we look at the logs and if
there's something wrong as i mentioned
uh my analysts go hold up that doesn't
look right and then we focus on what
might be happening around that lots of
software but you know i just want to say
something to your audience
capability isn't just software
capabilities
and process
if you have people processing a tool
that's capability and every combination
that three combination
software is an element is a tool to help
the process to help people okay it is
itself a capability does that make sense
and and therefore when your software
engineers are designing their code they
need to think people process they need
to think how it works together
and that's what we're looking for all
the time i'm not looking at software
i'm looking at how the software is being
used by people
to implement processes and if that
doesn't look right
that gives us an indicator that the baby
so a lot of the recovery uh of course
you've got your tools um you've got good
software practices good design practices
as we discussed but a lot also has to do
on process so uh that is also something
that has changed a lot in your
yeah and again um both time process and
the operational process so right you
need to look at all those processes so
clearly in the design process we've
we've introduced a beacon system which
allows us to see to make sure those
processes are being executed during the
design phase that's not a spine there's
a cab looking over the shoulder of the
developer that's that's there to help
the developer you know ensure
processes
but we're also looking in the
sustainment of that software that is
operated and we look again using beacons
as a wins to sort of see how those
processes are being worked and it's
important you know it's important
follow process
and that process gets logged we know the
right process has been followed we know
that's good
so yeah making sure the process has been
followed
good developer we'll do that pete's good
process
so the process and
people and technology is what is the key
uh that's that's from your recovery
perspective i guess so the other thing i
wanted to find out was also in terms of
you know you talked about your pattern
right with the secure pattern that you
have that also gets i guess improved uh
based every time like one of our
podcast episodes we also talked about
you know machine learning models built
for security and
there was this thing that you know the
machine learning models they also get
hacked
you know any thoughts on that like is uh
do you have any safeguards for that or
have you thought so far ahead
i mean most of what i've been talking
about by the way just to emphasize
you know this isn't just mercy this is a
global right
i wouldn't want your audience to walk
away saying say most of doing all of
this
personally
we're doing what most
most of the industry is doing or i guess
i'm repeating to your audience is the
good things that we're seeing and
implementing at the moment
but go back to your excellent question
ai is the future you know ai for all of
us is something we need to embrace we
need to look at ai
and and in security we look at ai from
two angles we look at ai as a way of
attacking us
so most of your audience be aware of
bottleneck
be subverted by to attack and deny
capability in the network and you know
there's areas where ai is getting really
smart they're using ai to do multi
password breaking you know they're
trying to hack passwords using ai so
they're using ai tools today against us
you know in order to try and attack us
on the other side we're using ai tools
to defend us i'll be honest with you to
do many of the things
we have to automatically i can't take 10
million logs scooty logs and manually go
through those logs i have to have
software and ai tools to look for
patterns and changes and difficulties
and that software and that pattern
behavior software that ai is so so so
important on the security side we're
seeing some great capabilities coming up
to the market you know uh watson's been
ibm watson has been there a while
looking at security patterns they're
using it in that space there are many
other companies
microsoft are doing the same with their
tooling so a lot of ai tooling has been
developed in the security space
what is the one worry i have and it's
the point raised
what would i do if i was a bad guy i
wouldn't attack my network i'm going to
attack the tool that i'm using to defend
my network
or or subvert it or try and disrupt it
because if i can disrupt the ai tool
they're using i can launch an attack
which might be more successful if that
makes sense so yes i'm it goes back to
my point about third party software
where we're using tools that we built by
others
and if i were a bad guy i would try and
get into those third-party supply chains
and just
just going back to the opening question
you asked me about the maersk attack the
musk attack wasn't onto a piece of
immersive software
the merck attack was launched through
third-party software that we were forced
to use that was provided by another
vendor and sustained by another vendor
so
we have got to like all the community
has got to get better at third party
software
security testing and evaluation
and that's your point about zero trust
network we can't trust software other
people
so we as a community become a little bit
more joined up out of the early days of
linux
we're not going to get to that
where i work also we sort of do that we
do check our third party open source
libraries hopefully we'll do that with
renewed vigor after this conversation so
i think i'd like to end the show with
asking you
i think what you alluded to this it's
only a matter of time before you get hit
by
any major company or you know small
startup could get hit by a cyber attack
so if there were three things that you
would uh you know give us advice uh
could you just you know three things
that you know we should keep in mind
there are three
that i think every company and we've
done it at first and it's three simple
principles we built three target
operating models around them the first
principle is risk
and understand the risk risks to your
network where are those risks where are
those vulnerabilities it comes with
visibility you need visibility so the
first thing is risk aligned with
visibility you need to know
where stuff is
and then understand what that risk is
the second piece is you need an
operational capability
immediately to deal with
events that occur proactively and
reactively you need to build that sort
of capability so a lot of big companies
don't have security operating centers
they don't have what i call the
goalkeeper
football fan big liverpool fan
what are the three things you need you
know you need a goalkeeper that's pretty
essential and that's what the security
op center provides you need that
goalkeeper who can operate
the processes and ensure things can work
if they were disruptive you know that's
that's the second piece that you saw and
the third piece that you saw is secured
by designers those three pieces of risk
operational capability to secure my
design get those three things correct in
any company in the right balance and
you're actually in a good place
okay that's great
thank you so much for this conversation
andy great thank you yeah it's been
great learning experience i think quite
different from what the other shows
we've done because we've looked at a
case study and i hope the listeners uh
enjoy so i just like to sign off and say
thank you for listening to everybody
this is priyanka raghavan for software
engineering radio
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se
radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening